Finding Aid for James J. Duderstadt Papers 1963-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Paper Documents
  - Position Papers 1984-1991, 0.25 linear feet
    The Position Papers (.25 linear ft., 1984-1991) are sets of documents in expandable folders, each focusing on a specific topic and each with a listing of its contents. The files are a combination of Duderstadt authored papers (some published in booklet form) and background material and articles about the subjects. Topics pertain to public service and the university; values, community, civility (diversity and the Michigan Mandate, for example); positions on vision and mission (includes 1986 environmental assessment); papers on acquisition and management of resources; and articles and papers on teaching and undergraduate education. As might be expected, this is an excellent source for attaining a broad view of the Duderstadt presidency. There is a master list to all of the documents in the first folder in the series.
    - Master List of Position Papers, Acquisition and Management of Resources 1984-1990 (Box 8)
    - Environmental Scanning and Vision / Mission and Role 1987-1991 (Box 8)
    - Public Service Faculty / Issues of Values, Community, Civility, Collegiality 1989-1991 (Box 8)
    - Teaching and Undergraduate Education / Research and Scholarship 1988-1990 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Mandate, Drafts, ca. 1988 (Box 22)
    - Public Service and the Public Research University, Draft 2.6 April 1989 (Box 22)
    - Some Observations Concerning the Future of the Public Research University March 28, 1996 (Box 22)
  - Publications (Legacy Documents) 1995-1996
    The Publications series, along with Position Papers, is a fine source for obtaining overviews of the goals and accomplishments of Duderstadt's presidency. These several items, published toward the end of Duderstadt's years in office are collectively entitled Legacy Documents. Handsomely housed in a hand-crafted clamshell box, the fourteen publications highlight the dramatic agenda pursued by the university under Duderstadt leadership from 1988-1996. Many of Duderstadt's speeches initially created in an outline form, which he considered the "poetic" version, are here finely reproduced in what he called the "full-prose" version.
    - Changing in a World of Change, 1995-1996 (Box 8)
    - State of the University Address, September 1995 (Box 8)
    - Diversity at the University of Michigan, Fall 1995 (Box 8)
    - Intellectual Transformation at the University of Michigan, Fall 1995 (Box 8)
    - The University of Michigan's Media Union, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Agenda for Women: A Report from the President, 1995 (Box 8)
    - The Michigan Mandate: A Seven-Year Progress Report, 1987-1994, November 1995 (Box 8)
    - Toward an Educational Transformation, Winter 1995 (Box 8)
    - Intercollegiate Athletics, Winter 1996 (Box 8)
    - The Cost, Price and Value of a College Education, Winter 1996 (Box 8)
    - A Strategy for Our Future, Spring 1996 (Box 8)
    - A Growing season: A Report from the President, The University of Michigan, 1986-1996, Spring 1996 (Box 8)
    - The University of Michigan Media Union, Summer 1996 (Box 8)
    - Rebuilding the University, 1986-1996, The University of Michigan, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Presentations 1972-1991 and undated
    The Presentations series (.50 linear ft., ca. 1972-1991 and not dated). The 2003 accession added to the limited number of presentations in the paper subgroup. The series now includes early versions of the Michigan Plan (ca. 1988), Nuclear Power: Technology on Trial, as well as the presentation of the Michigan Mandate to the Board of Regents on December 15, 1988. Researcher's should also consult the Digital Documents subgroup series entitled Presentations for related material.
    - Nuclear Power / Technology on Trial, circa 1973-1974, color slides (Box 8)
    - The Michigan Plan and The Challenge of Leadership, 5 folders; 1 folders (Box 8)
      (computer printouts of overheads with color specifications)
    - The Michigan Plan: A Strategy for the Enhancement of Excellence through Diversity, version 1.2 April 22, 1988 (Box 22)
    - The Michigan Plan: A Strategy for the Enhancement of Excellence through Diversity, version 1.4 May 1, 1988 (Box 22)
    - The Constellations of External Interactions March 1989 (Box 22)
    - Options for the 1990s and beyond..., December 1989 (Box 22)
    - Communication: External Constituencies January 1990 (Box 22)
    - Strategic Planning for the 1990s, October 1990 (Box 22)
    - Financing the Future: Resources for the 1990s and Beyond, January 1991 (Box 22)
    - Key Issues for the 1990s, February 1991 (Box 22)
    - State of Michigan Department of Education's Office of Equity Special Tribute, notes and press release May 1996 (Box 22)
    - Michigan Mandate, Regent's Meeting presentation December 15, 1988 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence circa 1967-1982
    The Correspondence series (1.5 linear ft., ca. 1967-1982) is largely comprised of correspondence between Duderstadt and various publishers regarding the publication of his numerous manuscripts and textbooks. The series also contains letters from a number of research fellows who wrote Duderstadt with updates on their research. The folder titled Ziya Akcasu is an example of the type of correspondence one will find in this series. The series is largely comprised of incoming correspondence.
    - June 1967-September 1969 (Box 9)
    - January 1970-December 1970 (Box 9)
    - January 1971-December 1971 (Box 9)
    - January 1972-September 1972 (Box 9)
    - January 1973-December 1973 (Box 9)
    - January 1974-December 1974 (Box 9)
    - January 1975-December 1975 (Box 9)
    - January 1976-December 1976 (Box 9)
    - January 1977-December 1977 (Box 9)
    - January 1978-December 1978 (Box 9)
    - January 1979-December 1979 (Box 9)
    - January 1980-December 1981 (Box 9)
    - Ziya Akcasu, Cekmece Nuclear Research Center, Istanbul, Turkey 1968-1970 (Box 10)
    - David Baen, correspondence 1971 (Box 10)
    - "Crackpot" correspondence 1979 (Box 10)
    - Employment opportunities 1970 (Box 10)
    - Neutron Transport Theory, correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 10)
    - Publishers (various) 1978-1980 (Box 10)
    - Reference Statements 1971-1978 (Box 10)
    - Research Fellows 1972-1976 (Box 10)
    - John Wiley & Sons, Inc. Publishers 1973-1982 (Box 10)
  - Research
    The Research series (6.0 linear ft., ca. 1969-1981), along with the Teaching series, provides an excellent reflection of Duderstadt's academic pursuits in nuclear engineering. The series contains a number of Air Force Office Scientific Research and National Science Foundation grant files as well as manuscripts and related materials for over fifty published manuscripts. The series also includes a sample of the reference files Duderstadt maintained on various nuclear engineering topics such as energy and rarefied dynamics. Overall, the series is a good example of nuclear engineering research activity in the 1970s as well as Duderstadt's role in the education of students at all levels. His keen interest in education can be seen in the development of an undergraduate engineering textbook authored with G.F. Knoll and G.S. Springer titled Principles of Engineering and through his role in the development of the nuclear engineering program at Michigan.
    - Address list for Reactor Physics 1969 (Box 10)
    - Article, "Nuclear Sewage Disposal," circa 1976 (Box 10)
    - Berward and Duderstadt, Design Study #1, A Laser-Driven Reactor for Radioactive Waste Transmutation: Preliminary Design Considerations November 25, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Code to Calculate the Kinetics of a CO2 Laser System for Either E-Beam Lasers or Axial Pulsed Lasers 1972, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Code to Calculate the Kinetics of a CO2 Laser System for Either E-Beam Lasers or Axial Pulsed Lasers 1973, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Conference presentation on Kinetic Theory circa 1980 (Box 10)
    - Dustin circa 1972 (Box 10)
    - Energy Deposition Distribution For Zero Width Source Code undated (Box 10)
    - Electronic Power Research Institute project 1975-1979 (Box 10)
    - Air Force Office of Scientific Research Grant files
      - Laser Diagnostics of Metallic Plasmas, Grant 74-2713 (1975-1978) (Box 10)
      - Theoretical Studies of Laser Light Interaction and Optical and X-Ray Emission from Dense, Metallic Plasmas," Grant 76-2904 circa 1977, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Theoretical Studies of Laser Light Interaction and Optical and X-Ray Emission from Dense, Metallic Plasmas," Annual Reports 1976-1980 (Box 10)
    - Laser Diagnostics of Metallic Plasmas, Grant 79-0030 circa 1979 (Box 11)
    - Theoretical Studies of the Propagation and Interaction of Intense Beams, Grant 80-0029 circa 1980 (Box 11)
    - Development of a Nuclear Engineering Code Library, Grant file circa 1977 (Box 11)
    - National Science Foundation Grant files
      - Theoretical Studies of Radiation Scattering from Dense, Many-Particle Systems, Grant 19360X 1973 (Box 11)
      - Applications to New Formulations of Statistical Mechanics to Fluctuation Phenomena, Grant 76-18903 circa 1976-1979, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Absorption of CO2 Laser Light in Dense Plasma, Grant 79-04820 circa 1979 (Box 11)
      - Theoretical Studies of the Interaction of Radiation with Systems Characterized by Random Behavior, Grant 79-12684 1979 (Box 11)
      - Theoretical Studies of the Interaction of Radiation with Gases, Liquids, and Plasmas, Grant 73-03860 1973-1976 (Box 11)
    - Inertial Confinement Fusion
      - Draft Text undated (Box 11)
      - Notes on Draft (Box 11)
    - Inertial Confinement Fusion Program (miscellaneous) undated (Box 11)
    - Laboratory Reports on KMS Fusion 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Manuscripts and Related Materials
      - An Accelerated Spectral Synthesis Technique, 1972-1974 (Box 12)
      - An Application of the Generalized Langevin Equation to the Study of Correlations in Simple, Classical Fluids, 1969 (Box 12)
      - Applications of the Degenerate Kernel Technique to Thermal Neutron Spectra Calculations, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Calculation of Current Correlation's in Classical Fluids via Modeled Kinetic Equations, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Characterization of an Ultradense Reproducible Z Pinch, 1978 (Box 12)
      - A Comparison of Projection Operator Formalisms for the Study of Self-Diffusion, 1973 (Box 12)
      - Computational Techniques in Nuclear Rector Analysis, undated (Box 12)
      - Convergence of the Finite Element Method in Neutron Transport 1975 (Box 12)
      - Convergence Properties of the Sn Algorithm, 1972 (Box 12)
      - The Degenerate Kernel Technique and Neutron Thermalization, 1969 (Box 12)
      - The Degenerate Kernel Technique and Neutron Thermalization Calculations in Asymptotic Reactor Theory, 1970 (Box 12)
      - The Derivation of Kinetic Equations from the Generalized Langevin Equation, 1969 (Box 12)
      - A Discrete Ordinates Solution of the Fokker-Planck Equation Characterizing Charged Particle Transport, 1978 (Box 12)
      - Energy RePresentations in Neutron Transport Calculations, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Finite Element Solutions of the Transport Equation with Applications to Strong Heterogeneities, circa 1976 (Box 12)
      - Fundamentals of Transport Theory, circa 1981 (Box 12)
      - An Improved Sn Inner Iteration Convergence Criterion, 1972 (Box 12)
      - An Improved Treatment of Electron Thermal Conduction in Plasma Hydrodynamics Calculations, 1976 (Box 12)
      - Inertial Confinement Fusion, draft text, undated (Box 12)
      - Inner Iteration Error in the Sn Algorithm, undated (Box 12)
      - Kinetic Theory Determination of the Density-Density Correlation Function in the One Component Plasma, 1986 (Box 12)
      - Laser Heating of a Dense Plasma Pinch, 1973-1974 (Box 12)
      - Lasers and Solid State Applications in Nuclear Engineering, 1975 (Box 12)
      - A Microscopic Theory of Density Fluctuations in Partially Ionized Gases, 1972 (Box 12)
      - A Modeled Kinetic Theory of Density Fluctuations in Plasmas circa 1972 (Box 12)
      - A Modeled Kinetic Theory of Gas Mixtures, undated (Box 12)
      - A Modeled Theory of Pulsed Neutron Experiments in Fast, Subcritical Assemblies, circa 1974 (Box 12)
      - Nuclear Power Generation, 1980 (Box 12)
      - Nuclear: No More? Or More than Ever?, 1979 (Box 12)
      - Neutronic Analysis of a Laser Fusion Driven Actinide Waste Burner, 1977 (Box 12)
      - Neutron Inelastic Scattering, 1972 (Box 12)
      - Nuclear Power Generation, 1977 (Box 12)
      - Nuclear Power--Technology on Trial, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
      - On the Continuous Eigenvalue Spectrum of the Neutron Wave Experiment, 1967 (Box 12)
      - Peturbative Theory of Self-Diffusion in Classical Many-Particle Systems. I. Velocity Autocorrelation Function, circa 1970 (Box 12)
      - Phase-Space Finite Element Methods Applied to the First-Order Form of the Transport Equation, circa 1981 (Box 12)
      - Ph.D., A Plasma Hydrodynamics Code For Laser Fusion Simulation Studies circa 1976 (Box 12)
      - Plasma Formation in E-Beam Co2 Lasers undated (Box 13)
      - Preliminary Design and Neutronic Analysis of Laser Fusion Driven Actinide Waste Burning Hybrid Reactor, circa 1978 (Box 13)
      - Principles of Engineering, proof copy, undated (Box 13)
      - Principles of Engineering, Solutions manual to accompany, undated (Box 13)
      - Projection Operator Methods in Time-Dependent Transport Theory, 1977 (Box 13)
      - Public Review of Nuclear Power Lacks Sufficient Scientific Basis, 1980 (Box 13)
      - Pulsed Neutron Measurements of Reactivity, 1971 (Box 13)
      - Radiation Transport in Dense Plasmas, undated (Box 13)
      - Ray Effect Elimination by Galerkin Finite Element Method, 1978 (Box 13)
      - Roundoff Error Analysis for the Sn Inner Iteration, 1972 (Box 13)
      - A Simple Model of Neutron Wave Propagation, 1967 (Box 13)
      - Spectral RePresentations for the Memory Kernel Characterizing Self-Diffusion, 1973 (Box 13)
      - Theory of Light Scattering from Dense Plasmas, 1972 (Box 13)
      - The Theory of Neutron Wave Propagation, 1968 (Box 13)
      - Theory of the Propagation of the Plane-Wave Disturbances in a Distribution of Thermal Neutrons, circa 1967 (Box 13)
      - Theory of Self-Diffusion in Classical Fluids, 1970 (Box 13)
      - Time Eigenvalues of the Neutron Transport Equation for Fast, Subcritical Assemblies, 1971 (Box 13)
      - Transport Equations for Dense Many Particle Systems, 1971 (Box 13)
      - A Transport Theory of Neutron Pulse Propagation, undated (Box 13)
      - A Transport Theory of Neutron Wave Propagation in Polycrystalline Media, 1967 (Box 13)
      - Wavelength Dependence of Laser-Light Absorption By A Solid Deuterium Target, 1971 (Box 13)
      - X-ray emission from laser-heated exploding wires, circa 1977 (Box 13)
      - Manuscript Reviews (published), various dates (Box 13)
      - Martin, William R (Box 13)
      - Melhorn and Duderstadt, Bull APS 22 1126 1977 (Box 13)
      - Melhorn and Duderstadt, IEEE 1978 (Box 13)
      - Monte Carlo Electron Transport With Constant Electric Field Code Listing circa 1973 (Box 13)
      - Naval Research Laboratory circa 1976 (Box 13)
      - Nuclear Power: Technology on Trial, correspondence 1973-1980 (Box 13)
      - Nuclear Reactor Analysis, Corrections to Text 1976-1981 (Box 13)
      - Neutron Transport Theory, Index and Corrections undated (Box 13)
      - Permissions for Nuclear Power, circa 1977 (Box 14)
      - Permissions for Principles of Engineering, circa 1980, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Presentations and Speeches 1976-1980 (Box 14)
    - Presentation, Michigan State Address "Nuclear Power: Problems and Prospects", undated (Box 14)
    - Projection Operator Techniques circa 1970 (Box 14)
    - Proposals
      - Calculation of the Deposition of Gamma Energy in Typical LWR Fuel Assemblies During Postulated Luca 1975 (Box 14)
      - Calculation of Time Correlation Functions For Liquids (Box 14)
      - Computation Schemes in Time-Dependent Neutron Thermalization circa 1970 (Box 14)
      - Development of A Computer Model of E-Beam Initiated Chemical Laser Kinetics 1974 (Box 14)
      - Development of a Finite Element Transport Code for Reactor Design Studies 1975 (Box 14)
      - Development of Modern Undergraduate Courses in Nuclear Reactor Analysis 1971 (Box 14)
      - Long-Wavelength Laser Heating of High Density Plasmas undated (Box 14)
      - Methods for Estimating Reactivity Worths and Depletion of strongly Localized Absorbers in Nuclear Reactors 1975 (Box 14)
      - Monitoring of Core Power Distributions in Nuclear Power Reactors 1975 (Box 14)
      - Proposal to Texas Instruments undated (Box 14)
      - Theoretical Studies of Electron Thermal Conduction in Laser-Fusion Plasmas circa 1976 (Box 14)
      - Theoretical Studies of Electron Thermal Conduction in Laser Heated Plasmas circa 1973 (Box 14)
      - Transient Analysis of Steam Generator Units in Nuclear Power Plants circa 1975 (Box 14)
    - Publication Contract for Inertial Confinement Fusion, circa 1980 (Box 14)
    - Recent Developments in Kinetic Theories, meeting 1976 (Box 14)
    - Reference Files
      - BVP in Gas Dynamics circa 1963 (Box 14)
      - Derivation of Neutron Transport (Box 14)
      - E-Beam circa 1974 (Box 14)
      - Electron Fields circa 1970 (Box 14)
      - Electron Transport (Box 14)
      - Energy (Box 14)
      - Energy-Dependent Transport Theory circa 1976 (Box 14)
      - Gas Atomic Physics circa 1973 (Box 14)
      - Kinetic Models (Box 14)
      - Kinetic Theory of Shocks (Box 14)
      - Kuscar, Ivan (Box 14)
      - Laser-Plasma in Garching circa 1971 (Box 14)
      - Leonard, A. circa 1964 (Box 14)
      - Linearized Boltzmann Equation (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous 1964-1970 (Box 14)
      - Monte Carlo Method (Box 14)
      - Nonlinear Boltzmann Equation (Box 15)
      - Numerical Methods circa 1975 (Box 15)
      - Perturbation Theory (Box 15)
      - Photon Transport (Box 15)
      - Physics (Box 15)
      - Plasma Shocks (Box 15)
      - Pulsed Neutron Experiments (Box 15)
      - Radiative Transfer (Box 15)
      - Rarefield Dynamics circa 1966 (Box 15)
      - Reactor Shielding (Box 15)
      - Resonance Absorption (Box 15)
      - Sound Propagation circa 1963 (Box 15)
      - Space Propolusion (Box 15)
      - Spectral Theory Gases circa 1965 (Box 15)
      - Spinrad, B., Neutron Transport Theory (Box 15)
      - Time Scaling Methods (Box 15)
      - Transport Theory circa 1975 (Box 15)
      - Turbulence, (fluid) (Box 15)
      - Turbulence, (general) (Box 15)
      - Variational Methods (Box 15)
      - Williams, M.R., Space Energy Separability in Pulsed Neutron Systems 1963 (Box 15)
    - Report on Plasma Formation in E-Beam Co2 Lasers 1973-1974 (Box 15)
    - Reports (miscellaneous) 1973-1976 (Box 15)
    - Steinke, Richard. A Review of Direct and Iterative Strategies for Solving Multi-Dimensional Finite Difference Problems (undated) (Box 15)
    - Student Support 1977-1978 (Box 15)
    - University of Michigan Plasma Laboratory 1974-1975 (Box 15)
    - University of Michigan Press Nuclear Power: Technology on Trial, circa 1978 (Box 15)
    - U.S. Army Missile Command, Redstone Arsenal Alabama circa 1972 (Box 15)
  - Topical Files 1971-1991
    The Topical Files (1.50 linear ft., 1971-1991) is limited in scope, holding papers mainly from Dr. Duderstadt's involvement on various committees within the Department of Nuclear Engineering. The bulk of these materials are from the years just preceding his appointment to Dean of the College of Engineering. An interesting, yet not dated, written document titled, "Thoughts on A Rainy Day, on moving the College of Engineering to North Campus" may be the initial seed for the ultimate move of the College of Engineering from central campus to the North Campus in the mid-1980s. The remainder of the series is comprised of papers associated with his term as provost. The largest file is entitled "Contacts," and includes memos, cards and letters, message slips, lists of meeting attendees, hand-written notes, and other miscellany. Of particular significance is a list of key activities for 1981 to 1985 relating to Duderstadt's accomplishments in the College of Engineering, and the farewell address (with annotations) that he gave to engineering staff upon leaving. Also important are notes entitled "Vision of the University" that Duderstadt prepared while he was being considered for the provost position. In addition, there is a small correspondence file, significant partly because there is so little "traditional" correspondence from his year's as president in the collection as a whole. The 2003 accession added one linear feet of material concerning Duderstadt's role on the National Science Board in the early 1990s.
    - Contacts (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1983-1988 (Box 16)
    - Farewell Address (College of Engineering) April 7, 1986 (Box 16)
    - Notes 1981-1986 (Box 16)
    - American Nuclear Society
      - Planning Committee, Publication Reports (Box 16)
      - Agendas and Meeting Minutes 1977-1980 (Box 16)
      - Michigan Section Correspondence 1979 (Box 16)
      - Membership Direction, Michigan Section (Box 16)
    - Academic Affairs Advisory Committee
      - Correspondence 1977-1979 (Box 16)
      - Meeting Minutes 1977-1979 (Box 16)
    - College of Engineering History file undated (Box 16)
    - Committee on Public Administration 1979 (Box 16)
    - Course and Academic Program material 1976-1979 (Box 16)
    - Curriculum Committee reports 1973-1979 (Box 16)
    - Departmental Review Committee, correspondence 1978-1979 (Box 16)
    - Department of Nuclear Engineering, Departmental Materials, miscellaneous 1971-1975 (Box 16)
    - Department of Nuclear Engineering Review Background Material circa 1979 (Box 16)
    - Department of Nuclear Engineering Review Committee Report February 1979 (Box 16)
    - Employment Patterns for Nuclear Engineering 1975-1977 (Box 16)
    - Engineering-Mathematics Committee 1969-1983 (Box 16)
    - Engineering-Mathematics-Statistics Committee, Agendas and Meeting Minutes 1975-1983 (Box 16)
    - Evaluations of Faculty Research Grants 1975-1979 (Box 16)
    - Evaluation of Faculty Research Grants Report 1979 (Box 16)
    - Faculty Awards, 1977-1979 (Box 16)
    - Faculty Search Committee 1979-1980 (Box 16)
    - A Guide to Nuclear Engineering Students Interested in Fission Reactors undated (Box 16)
    - Prelim Committee 1976-1979 (Box 17)
    - A Proposal for Master's Level Education In Remote Sensing, Rackham Executive Committee 1979 (Box 17)
    - Rackham Executive Board 1978-1979 (Box 17)
    - Report of the Ad Hoc Space Committee, Cooley Laboratory Move circa 1977 (Box 17)
    - Report of the Ad Hoc Committee to Review the Department of Mechanical Engineering 1978 (Box 17)
    - Report on Inter-College Programs undated (Box 17)
    - A Report on Research Incentives, Advisory Committee on Academic Affairs 1979-1980 (Box 17)
    - Report of the Subcommittee to review the University Extension Service 1981 (Box 17)
    - Subcommittee to review the University Extension Service, background materials and correspondence 1981, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Rules of the Faculty of the College of Engineering 1973 (Box 17)
    - Thoughts on a Rainy Day, on moving the College of Engineering to North Campus undated (Box 17)
    - National Academy of Engineering November 1987 (Box 24)
    - National Science Board
      - Appointment materials, ca. 1985 (Box 24)
      - Meeting Minutes and Related Materials
        - 1990, 2 folders (Box 24)
        - 1991 (Box 24)
        - 1992 (Box 24)
        - 1993 (Box 24)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposal, Management and Operation of the NSFNET Backbone Network August 1987 (Box 24)